Finding Aid for Hull Family Papers, 1870-1870
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hull Family Papers, 1870-1970
Hull Family
1 linear foot
91437 Aa 2
Letters, 1888-1899, of George Hull, Livingston County, Michigan, farmer, to his son Lawrence then attending Lawrenceville School in New Jersey relating to the family's fruit farm at Pleasant Lake; papers of Lawrence's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, student at the University of Michigan; papers of Lawrence and Eliza's son Leroy relating to World War I service; diaries of Leroy's wife, Frances Bell Hull, 1915-1919 and 1947-1957; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Jean Hull Ruhman and Mr. John Ruhman (donor number 7826 ) in July 1990.
The collection is open to research.
The Hull family has been prominent in Michigan's Washtenaw, Livingston, and Wayne Counties since the first representatives of the family arrived in the state in 1833. George Hull (1827-1912) and his wife Isabelle were farmers. They owned their first farm in Saline, farmed in Hamburg Township from 1870 to 1883, and spent their final years working a fruit farm at Pleasant Lake in Livingston County. Their son, Lawrence C. Hull (1857-1916), attended school in Lawrenceville, New Jersey. He became a well-known school administrator at the Lawrenceville School and later at the Michigan Military Academy. Lawrence's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, attended the University of Michigan from 1878 to 1882.
Lawrence and Eliza Hull's son, Leroy Wetmore Hull (1888-1972) became a prominent Detroit area physician. A graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School Class of 1911, Leroy served in World War I and later became president of the Wayne County Medical Society, the Detroit Academy of Medicine, the Michigan State Medical Society, and the American Urological Association. His wife, Frances E. Ball Hull (1896-1987) was active in community affairs.
A family tree of the Hull Family as well as further biographical information can be found in the first folder of the collection.
The Hull Family Collection consists of one linear foot of material containing letters, diaries, photos, clippings, and ephemera. It is arranged by family member in a rough chronological order. Following a folder of biographical material are folders of material regarding George Hull and his wife, Isabelle, their son, Lawrence C. Hull and his wife, Eliza Darling Hull, and then information regarding Leroy W. Hull and his wife, Frances Bell Hull.
The material on George and Isabelle Hull consists largely of correspondence from 1888-1899, primarily from George Hull to his son, Lawrence, who was then away at school in Lawrenceville, New Jersey. The letters give some insights into life on the Hull family farm at Pleasant Lake. There is also an early photo of George and Isabelle.
The Lawrence Hull material includes a family photo, a few personal papers, and materials from his tenure at the Michigan Military Institute. There are also two volumes of the novel The Varmint by Owen Johnson (1910). The book depicts life at the Lawrenceville School in the 1890s. The character of "The Old Roman" was based on Lawrence Hull (see page 398 of the autographed edition). A movie based on the novel was made with Leo G. Carroll playing the part of Lawrence Hull for which photos are included.
Lawrence Hull's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, attended the University of Michigan and several of her student papers from both her high school days in LaPorte, Indiana and UM are included (1873-1882). These are well-written essays on a variety of subjects, including one on the plight of the American Indian and one on coeducation. Eliza's diary from 1896-1900 while her husband was at Lawrenceville School is also in the collection.
The materials on Lawrence and Eliza Hull's son, Leroy W. Hull, make up a large portion of the collection. There is one folder of photos including those of the U of M Medical School Class of 1911. There is also a folder of correspondence from Leroy, primarily to his sister Grace, regarding his service in World War I. Dr. Hull's professional activities are documented through photographs, clippings, bulletins, and other material generated by various professional societies. Also included are some photos from a medical tour Dr. Hull made to Vietnam in the 1960s.
Dr. Hull's wife, Frances Ball Hull (1886-1987) was a member of Detroit Central High School's Class of 1915. Included in the collection are her high school yearbook and her diaries from 1915-19 and 1947-57.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Livingston County.; Fruit.; Hamburg (Mich.: Township); Hull family.; Lawrenceville School.; Livingston County (Mich.); Orchards.; Physicians--Michigan--Wayne County.; Physicians' spouses--Michigan--Wayne County.; Pleasant Lake (Livingston County, Mich.); Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hull family.; Vietnam.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family materials
  - Biographies and family tree (Box 1)
- George L. Hull and Isabelle M. Hull
  - Photo and obituary (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1888 1894-1899 (Box 1)
- Lawrence C. Hull and Eliza Darling Hull
  - Lawrence C. Hull
    - Personal (photos) (Box 1)
    - Michigan Military Institute (Box 1)
    - Photos from movie, The Varmint (Box 1)
  - Eliza Darling Hull
    - Student papers, 1873-1882 (Box 1)
    - Diary, 1896-1900 (Box 1)
- Isabelle McFarlane Hull
  - Travel accounts, 1923-1951 (sister of Dr. Leroy Hull) (Box 1)
- Dr. Leroy Hull and Frances Ball Hull
  - Dr. Leroy Hull
    - Photos (Box 1)
    - World War I correspondence (Box 1)
    - Professional activities-clippings (Box 1)
    - Professional activities (with photos) (Box 1)
    - Vietnam photos (Box 1)
  - Frances Ball Hull
    - Detroit Central HS Class of 1915 (Box 1)
    - Diaries, 1915-1919 1953-1955 (Box 1)
Related Material
The Detroit Historical Museum has additional Hull family materials.